[Music]
welcome to the real news network i'm
paul jay
welcome to reality asserts itself john
keriaku
is in his house waiting for another 40
days
before he's free to walk out the front
door he's under house arrest
after spending 23 months in jail john
kariakou was born on august 9
1964. he's a former cia analyst and case
officer a former senior investigator for
the senate foreign relations committee
and a former counter-terrorism
consultant for abc news
he was the first u.s government official
to confirm in december 2007
that waterboarding was used to
interrogate al-qaeda prisoners which he
described as torture
on october 22nd 2012 karyaku pleaded
guilty to disclosing classified
information about a fellow cia
officer that connected the covert
operative to a specific operation
he was the first person to pass
classified information to a reporter
although the reporter did not publish
the name of the operative he was
sentenced to 30 months in prison on
january 25th
2013 and he served his term from
february 28
2013 until the 3rd of february 2015 at a
low security federal correctional
facility
in loreto pennsylvania when john joined
the cia in 1990 he was 25 years old
he was a true believer in americanism
american exceptionalism as some people
call it
and now he's not and that's what this
interview is about and now john joins us
thank you very much thanks for having me
so
we're going to do a many segments of
this interview because
you've lived a lot of different lives in
the cia
um and i think just to establish the
ground rules
some of what we're going to ask john is
classified and i'm going to not
not not ask him i'm going to ask him
whatever we feel like asking him
and then he's going to figure out if
there's times he has to say well i can't
say that because it's classified and
then he'll parse what he can say
but just to let you know that's going to
happen once in a while
but probably not at the beginning
because i don't think any of you growing
up is classified
no so in the beginning we want to talk
about
how you become americanized and how much
that's part of your personal identity
so your your parents are greek yes
you're of greek origin yes
and and when does your family come to
the united states
my mother's parents came i should say my
father's parents came in february 1931
and my mother's parents followed three
years later
growing up to hear my grandfather tell
the story franklin roosevelt
personally allowed him in the country
got him a job in a steel mill in
canonsburg pennsylvania
and by god we were going to be democrats
for the rest of our lives
to repay the kindness that franklin
roosevelt showed
in fact into the 1970s until my
grandfather's death in 1978
he had a framed photo of franklin
roosevelt sitting on top of the
television set so i always grew up
with a feeling that i had to repay the
kindness that the country had shown my
family
that we had a debt to the democratic
party specifically to franklin roosevelt
and that public service was something
to which i should aspire and what did
your father and mother do
my dad was an elementary school
principal for 42 years
and my mother was a third grade teacher
and
they sort of internalized all this fdr
and america adoration oh yes yeah very
much so
very much so even as a even as a child
i was active politically because my
parents were
even as an eight-year-old a
nine-year-old i was a it was even
earlier than that an eight-year-old
i was a volunteer on the mcgovern
campaign stuffing envelopes and such
and then even when i went to college the
first thing i did literally on my first
day in college was to join the college
democrats
and after roosevelt we have truman
did that loyalty transfer on president
to president in other words did you grow
up with the narrative that dropping the
bomb on hiroshima and nagasaki
was somehow for the greater good i
remember a relative
of mine saying truman taught the japs a
thing or two
uh and i i'll add too that
there was at least as much love for
harry truman as there was for franklin
roosevelt in our family
because it was truman that saved greece
from communism
and my grandparents were very grateful
for that
and where you know much of greece was
pro-communist so
where did your father coming in the 30s
where did they get their anti-communism
from
well my grandfather was a voracious
consumer of news
which was hard to do in the early 1940s
but but still he he consumed as much
news
about greece as he could whether it was
from life magazine
or time magazine copies of which i still
have as a matter of fact
that mention greece or letters to and
from relatives in greece he really
stayed up on what was
going on he was also a member of two
greek american organizations
the american hellenic educational and
progressive association
a hepa and gapa the greek american
progressive association both
well i should say kappa was really a
liberal group
but it it supported using greek
the greek language in the home and ahepa
was more pan-political but encouraged
newly arrived greeks to assimilate and
to become americans
and to speak english in the home my
grandfather was a member of both
organizations
because because roosevelt worked with
the soviet union against hitler
for many years roosevelt's vice
president wallace right if he if he had
been able to stay on his vice president
he got dumped by the party that's right
in favor of truman
uh was very much for working with the
soviet soviet union was against this
kind of beginning of a cold war
so like moving from roosevelt to truman
it's not a natural progression in terms
of especially when it comes to greece
because when you say save greece from
communism
it was by installing dictators in greece
it was not like some democracy they came
but there was
there was even some disagreement in the
home my grandmother was very
conservative
and although she was a democrat she
became a democrat once she became a
citizen
she was a lifelong royalist where when
it came to greek politics
but are they from she was she from the
working class oh yes very much so
very much so her mother died at a young
age and
her father believed that his three
daughters should
have a trade have an education my
grandmother was the only one of her
sisters that went to school
and became a teacher and then a
translator for the italian occupation
government
she taught italian soldiers to speak
greek her sisters were
a dressmaker uh and uh
and her youngest sister ended up owning
a a gas station and a butcher shop
so there was always there was always
this uh
drive to succeed even though they were
women that my great-grandfather had
instilled so so in the narrative of your
families when it comes to greece
and that the installation of a
dictatorship somehow was a good thing
and somehow that's for democracy it
depended on the dictatorship my
grandparents were really worried about
communism in greece in the 1940s because
the communists were killing a lot of
innocent people they would go into
villages to recruit men
and any man that didn't want to go back
up into the mountains to fight for the
greeks was killed
and oftentimes the the wives and
children were killed as well
well i'm i'm not going to argue with you
about it but i've interviewed
greek communists who fought the nazis
and then but afterwards and you get
quite a different story
sure oh of course you do and and still
these three generations later you're
still going to get arguments on both
sides yeah
but at any rate this is part of your
formation yeah
america fights for the greater good and
as i've said on the real news a few
times that
it's sort of like we do bad things but
for the for good reasons
right i believed that for many years
decades
i don't believe that anymore so when we
get
to you in the high school so you're born
in 64
vietnam war is ending as you kind of
start becoming much more conscious of
politics
as you head into college what's your
vision of the world and your place in it
what you might be doing
i considered myself at the time to be
what was then called
a social democrat liberal
on social issues economic issues
and then pretty hawkish on foreign
policy and defense
i remember there being in retrospect a
very funny debate
within the college democrats at gw over
the invasion of grenada
should we issue a statement should we
issue a statement condemning
the invasion of grenada these are like
six
college freshmen and sophomores debating
whether we should issue a statement like
anybody
cared and i remember opposing a
statement because
i supported the invasion of grenada i
don't recall why
uh but i did i felt i i guess that it
was
it showed a robust foreign policy and it
showed that we were willing to go out
and protect our citizens and
we needed a win yeah we needed a win it
had been a while since
since we had had a win um but all
through college i was pretty hawkish on
on foreign policies you were also
excuse me in a little bit weird way very
interested in politics and leaders
didn't you at some point write a letter
to the shah and you got a signed
right right what was that all about i
think i was 14 or 15.
i wrote a letter to the shah of iran
i wrote to tell them that i was i was
disgusted by the way our government had
treated him
that once we had made a decision we
should have stuck with the decision and
the decision had been to allow him to
come to the united states
for treatment of his cancer and when
the heat got a little more than the
president could handle the shah was
unceremoniously thrown out and ended up
in
panama and then later the bahamas so i
wrote him a letter saying
it's terrible the way you were treated
and he actually wrote me a letter back
saying you're right it's terrible the
way i've been treated here's an
autographed picture he probably didn't
get many letters like that
no i sure didn't what motivated you
i don't know i was just so interested in
foreign affairs that it just seemed like
a
natural thing to do i followed the iran
hostage crisis
day by day by day for example and even
though nightline was on very late at
night for a
you know 14 year old or 15 year old i
stayed up every single night and watched
ted koppel on nightline because
originally nightline was to give us a
daily update of events in iran
you know they have a day count that's
right so many days more and
that's right and so i was just
fascinated by it and i remember telling
my father we were in the car together
and my dad for whatever reason always
wanted me to become a dentist
and i remember telling him dad i really
don't want to be a dentist
and he said well what do you want to do
and i said i think i want to join the
foreign service
and i was 14. i was 14 i guess
at the time and he said well whatever
you want to do
just do it well and you wrote margaret
thatcher
i did but your choice of leaders are all
they were very conservative very
conservative they were very conservative
i got it i got an autographed picture
from azer weissman the uh
at the time the defense minister of
israel these are people that today i
wouldn't dream of writing a letter
of support to but but back then i was
pretty hawkish
was there anyone influencing you in this
direction or was kind of just your own
no no it was just it was my own thing it
was my own interest
so you go to college and what do you
study middle eastern studies
why i don't know i
i was fascinated with the middle east a
couple of people
um asked me if i was interested in
hellenic studies i could have
i could have studied at georgetown or or
i mean there are several different
places
that you can study hellenic studies good
schools and i said no i was more
interested in the middle east and then
my dad
in an attempt to get me to stay close to
home said
well you know the university of
pittsburgh has a great eastern european
studies program
and i said i don't care about eastern
european studies i don't care about the
soviet union i truly didn't
i only cared about the middle east and
there were three schools in the country
at the time
that had middle eastern studies programs
george washington
rutgers and brigham young and george
washington was the easy choice
now as you you know into the late 70s
in the early 80s you know you're coming
to consciousness
you know political you're interested in
foreign affairs how does
as the revelations of what really
happened in vietnam
and what a lie mostly lies that
war was based on you know there's
there's quotes from senior
johnson officials near the end of the
war that that if
70 percent of the reason we're in
vietnam is just to prove
how strong we are it's now become 100 of
the reason for being
in vietnam and you hear that under nixon
but that it became just about proving to
the world we can't lose a war
meaning tens of thousands of lives i
mean really millions of lies
including you know maybe perhaps at
least three million vietnamese
right cambodians and and thousands of
american soldiers
does that not in some way start to shake
your americanism
not at first in fact and i haven't
thought about this in
years but i remember an argument that i
got into with a friend of mine
in the college democrats over vietnam
and i said that i had opposed the war
not had opposed i opposed the war
i thought it was immoral i thought it
was illegal but if i had been drafted
i would have gone and he said if he had
been drafted he would have gone to
canada
and we had a real argument about that
and he said to me how can you oppose a
war
and then go fight in it and i said
because my country asked me to
um i wouldn't give that same answer
today
but as an 18 year old that's what i
believed
but you did think it was immoral and
illegal i did because a lot of the
leaders you're writing to and so on i
mean they would have
in fact i introduced george mcgovern
when he announced his candidacy for
president
in uh september of 1984. yeah i saw that
and in his in
in my speech of introduction i said that
he was one of the few senators
to stand up to the illegal and immoral
war in vietnam
that seemed a little contradictory with
all the other positions you were doing i
was a kid supporting granada
19 at the time yeah still figuring it
out
still figuring it out we used to go to
the white house uh
at night when you could walk right up to
the gate and shout
can i swear on this program and shout
you reagan
you know based on something we had seen
on the news that night and
but you're supposed to be the invasion
of great differences yeah i know right
so
you reagan at the fence and then
i'd go back to the college democrats and
say
you know guys i gotta go with reagan on
this one
[Laughter]
but still the underlying thing is
america
can really do no wrong maybe mistakes
maybe
errors that's exactly how i felt sure we
made mistakes
certainly but our hearts were in the
right place
i really believed that that we were that
you know shining city on a hill
back then and for many years later
really
until september 11th i believe that
well we're going to get to that in the
continuation of our series of interview
with john
we're going to ask him how he got
recruited into the cia
please join us for the next in our
series of interviews on reality asserts
itself
on the real news network
[Music]
you